# **Wayne Starron**

# **CPG Quality Professional**

Quality professional with 30+ years of experience in both manufacturing and R&D settings. Skilled in managing both people and processes. I've supervised from 1 to 31 staff members at a time with all levels of education, experience, and job titles. Over 25 years of GLP and GMP experience in both EPA and FDA environments. Over 10 years experience with ISO 9001, 14001, 18001, & FSSC 22000 quality systems. Certified in HACCP, PCQI, and Internal Auditor. Well versed in CAPA systems, as well as 5S & Kaizen Continuous Improvement. I take a handson approach to make sure the work is completed per protocol. Providing exceptional customer service with on-time quality results is my prime motivator.

# **Experience**

# 2015-11 - Quality Assurance Manager

2017-12

Coca-Cola Refreshments

Managed a department of 25 people (supervisors, lab technicians and production workers).

Key Accomplishments:

- Leader of the facility Food Safety and HACCP teams.
- One of the many quality metrics I monitored is Consumer Complaints per Million (CPM). The plant CPM was 0.78 when I started as QA Manager. When I left the YTD CPM was 0.57. This currently ranks in the top 5 for all Carbonated Soft Drink bottlers in North America.
- Lead the plant teams responsible for ISO 9001, 22001 and FSSC 22000 certification. Also, worked with the Safety Manager and other senior management to get the facility their initial ISO 14001 and 18001 Safety and Environmental certifications.
- When I arrived at the plant there were over 200 Corrective Actions on the books from previous internal and external audits. When I left there were less than 5 and those were well on their way to resolution.
- Scored a 905 and an 870 on our most recent AIB external audits; the 905 was 2nd highest in North America for a carbonated soft drink manufacturing facility in the Coca-Cola Bottling system.

# 2013-09 - Production Manager

2015-11

G.S. Cosmeceutical USA, Inc.

I also worked here in the same role from May 2006-Jan 2008. Key Accomplishments/Responsibilities:

- Supervised 8-12 production blenders, coordinating production schedule with Customer Service, ensuring products are made on time with no resource conflicts.
- Key member of the Oracle ERP Software Development and Implementation team. Designed inputs, suggested updates and corrections during testing phases, and developed tutorials for Batch Ticket and Raw Material tracking and consumption.
- Verify raw material inventory for scheduled production and coordinate with Purchasing, Quality, Customer Service and Shipping & Receiving to ensure material availability. Order and maintain consumables needed for production.
- Work with Facilities group to get maintenance and calibration activities done in a timely manner to minimize impact on manufacturing schedule. Personally perform calibration verification tasks on selected manufacturing equipment (flow meters, scales, etc.).

## **Personal Info**

#### **Address**

3612 Ashwood Drive Pleasanton, CA 94588

#### **Phone**

925-351-6852 (Mobile) 925-461-1491 (Home)

#### E-mail

wstarron@comcast.net

#### Date of birth

1964-07-17

#### LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/wstarron/

## **Skills**

Staff Development and Growth

Team Building & Leadership

CAPA Management

Certified HACCP, PCQI, Internal Auditor

Oracle, Microsoft Access and SAP experience

5S & Kaizen Continuous Improvement

Management of Union personnel

- Used my Kaizen training to reorganize the Bulk Production department, allowing more work to happen in parallel. Reduced the batch processing time by 30-40% and lowered overtime hours in the Production staff by 20%.
- Worked with Quality and R&D departments to upgrade the GMP documentation for production equipment. Re-designed the forms to be less confusing and easier for the users to fill out while keeping all essential data available for review.

### 2008-01 - Director of Technical Services

**2013-03** Royal Chemical Co.

I was both the QA and R&D Manager for a custom chemical blender, toll and contract manufacturer of industrial, institutional and household cleaning products. Key Responsibilities:

- Administered plant Nonconforming Material Report (NMR) and CAPA programs. Coordinated with company headquarters on multi-plant NMRs and CAPAs.
- Created, implemented and maintained a QC lab instrument PM schedule.
  Worked with vendors and outside agencies to keep GMP lab equipment working within specifications and delivering accurate results.
- Led a multi-facility project to merge and streamline the ISO work instructions across all five Royal Chemical facilities, merging separate systems into one.
- Acted as lead audit manager for customers that have Designed for the Environment (DfE) registered products during NSF International audits. All audits passed with no major notations.
- Established and maintained QC lab equipment calibration and maintenance logs, coordinating external calibration services and internal routine GMP internal calibrations. Served as QC department representative for external ISO and customer audits.

### 2003-08 - QA Supervisor

**2006-02** Ghirardelli Chocolate Co.

I supervised all 3 shifts' QC lab technicians, who were responsible for all raw material, in process and finished product testing and release. Key Accomplishments:

- Converted paper QA lab data storage and analysis system, equipment calibration and maintenance records to electronic using Microsoft Access. This reduced data entry time 17% and data analysis time over 75%.
- Assumed 2 manufacturing position duties concurrently while throughput remained constant at full staff levels on all three shifts. Result: Successfully managed a 40% technician staff reduction for 8 weeks during peak production season.
- Administered plant Nonconforming Material Report (NMR) and CAPA investigations and reported results to QA Manager. Coordinated out-of-spec chocolate rework with Production.

### 1987-09 - Senior Scientist

**2002-12** The Clorox Company

Started as a Scientist I. Promoted to Scientist II in 1992. Worked as Division Quality Supervisor for the Hidden Valley division from 1994-1995. Key Accomplishments:

• Developed uniform validation procedure for all new and existing test methods. Result: Shortened typical product development timelines 7-10%; reduced test

•

- method development and training time 20%.
- Conducted Customer Complaint investigations and reported results to Quality Assurance department for CAPA program.
- Established initial NLEA nutritional database for Hidden Valley Ranch and KC Masterpiece product lines via both in-house analysis and coordination with outside laboratory services.
- Analytical Department Safety Coordinator for 2 years. No incidents during that time.
- Applied chemometric modeling to calculate quantities of colored dye and optical brightener required in samples to install an automatic in-line analyzer.
   Result: Improved testing efficiency 3600%.
- While at Hidden Valley Ranch:
- Evaluated scientific merit of existing test procedure. Concluded test results were non-repeatable, irrelevant and non-verifiable. Convinced management to abandon procedure. Result: Saved \$2,000,000 annually.
- Received all HV customer complaints, wrote exception reports, conducted root cause analyses, determined product dispositions and implemented CAPAs.
- Hired and trained 12 temporary lab technicians to properly conduct complex test procedures and evaluate results to support a fast-track product launch.
   Result: Reduced product development timeline 76%, product launched on time.
- Refined and updated the plant HACCP program, revising it from an unwieldy 122 critical control points to a more manageable 25 CCPs. Result: Program more easily and consistently administered, with no violations occurring during my time as administrator.

# **Education**

1983-09 - California State University, Hayward

**1987-06** Bachelor of Science, Chemistry degree